<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rich: Nugents Cynthia Containing direfull sonnets, madrigalls, and passionate intercourses, describing his repudiate affections expressed in loues owne language.</title>
            <title>Cynthia</title>
            <author>Nugent, Richard, fl. 1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18745</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110185</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845781</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845781</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10702</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10702)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rich: Nugents Cynthia Containing direfull sonnets, madrigalls, and passionate intercourses, describing his repudiate affections expressed in loues owne language.</title>
                  <title>Cynthia</title>
                  <author>Nugent, Richard, fl. 1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] P[urfoot] for Henrie Tomes, and are to be sould at his shop by Graies Inne new gate in Holborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RICH: NVGENTS <hi>Cynthia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>CONTAINING Direfull Sonnets, Madrigalls, and paſsionate intercourſes, deſcribing <hi>his repudiate affections expreſſed</hi> in Loues owne Language.</p>
            <q>Non ad imitandum, ſed ad precauendum.</q>
            <p>Diſce ex me.</p>
            <p>LONDON <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Printed by T. P. for Henrie Tomes, and are to be ſould at his ſhop by Graies Inne new gate in <hi>Holborne. 1604.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:2"/>
            <l>O multa dictu grauia: perpeſsu aſpera.</l>
            <l>Quae exantlato corpore at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> animo pertuli</l>
            <l>Feminea vi, femineo interimor vultu.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:2"/>
            <head>The Dedication of this <hi>Booke.</hi> To the right honourable the Ladie of <hi>Trymleſtowne.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>LAdie moſt worthy, of moſt eſtimation,</l>
            <l>In whome all goodneſſe is together knit,</l>
            <l>Whoſe vertues purchaſe fame, fame admiration,</l>
            <l>Of holyeſt will, ioyn'd with a heau'nly wit,</l>
            <l>Whoſe praiſe, if I would ſhew by word, or writ,</l>
            <l>(A Theame too hye for <hi>Ciceroes</hi> Oration)</l>
            <l>My words, from my thoughts reach as low would flet,</l>
            <l>As my thoughts reach, from ſo high contemplatien:</l>
            <l>Receiue in gree, this ill agreeing matter,</l>
            <l>An idle worke in idle houres diſpatcht:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Perſian</hi> King, whoſe power the world did threat,</l>
            <l>Tooke in good worth a poore mans cup of water,</l>
            <l>Who needes not ſcorne a whit to be thus matcht,</l>
            <l>If to be good, be more than to be great.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:3"/>
            <head>The firſt part.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. I.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Planet, whoſe ſwift courſe diuides the times</l>
               <l>And warmes the earth, that ſhe her burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yelds</l>
               <l>Approached now vnto our northerne clymes.</l>
               <l>Leauing the ſcorched <hi>Aethiopian</hi> felds;</l>
               <l>The birds, that in that ſeazon ſtill reioyce,</l>
               <l>To ſee their wythred bowers new clad with greene,</l>
               <l>Did ſummon me, in their ſweet warbling voice,</l>
               <l>To giue attendance on the Summers Queene:</l>
               <l>I ſtraight obeyd, and by two Chriſtall ſtreames</l>
               <l>That through a pleaſant groue forth murmering ſlide,</l>
               <l>I layd me downe, and viewd bright <hi>Phorbus</hi> beames,</l>
               <l>Which mounted from the Eaſt, with gliſtring pride.</l>
               <l>But ſoone my minde and lookes from thence allured</l>
               <l>Two Sonnes, whoſe light had <hi>Phoebus</hi> light obſcured.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>TWo Sonnes, whoſe light had <hi>Phoebus</hi> light obſcured,</l>
               <l>Firing with their bright beams, the neighbour brooks,</l>
               <l>Mine eyes, with wonder and delight allured,</l>
               <l>Vpon themſelues, to bend their curious looks;</l>
               <l>When loe, I ſpide a Nimph of peereleſſe beautie,</l>
               <l>In whoſe white face, thoſe planets faire were fixed,</l>
               <l>To whome in lowly wiſe, I did my dutie,</l>
               <l>Of feare, and reuerent loue, together mixed,</l>
               <l>But ſhe, my fainting voice no ſooner heard,</l>
               <l>And ſaw where on the ground I groueling lay,</l>
               <l>Then like the trembling Deere, of Hound afeard,</l>
               <l>Backe through the ſhadey groue ſhe hyed away:</l>
               <l>Away ſhe hyed, and when I loſt her ſight,</l>
               <l>My Summers day ere noone, was turned to night.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:3"/>
               <head>Sonet. III.</head>
               <l>MY Summers day, ere noone, was turn'd to night,</l>
               <l>And now no light frequents my darkeſome bower,</l>
               <l>For ſince that houre, that my faire <hi>Cynthiaes</hi> eyes,</l>
               <l>Did mine ſurpriſe, with their diuine aſpect,</l>
               <l>Yet no reſpect would haue to my reliefe,</l>
               <l>Blacke nights of griefe, ſucceed my Summers day.</l>
               <l>O beautious <hi>May,</hi> ſo may thy beautie flouriſh,</l>
               <l>The Heauen ſo nouriſh may thy blooming floures,</l>
               <l>And fertile ſhowes raine downe of happineſſe,</l>
               <l>Still ſtill to bleſſe thy dayes, as thou wilt deine</l>
               <l>To rew my paine, and ſound my woes retreat,</l>
               <l>That growes ſo great, becauſe thou grow'ſt ſo beautious.</l>
               <l>Looke on thoſe dutious eyes, behold alas,</l>
               <l>The watry glaſſe, where thou thy ſelfe mayſt view,</l>
               <l>And let that hew, that firſt procur'd my paine,</l>
               <l>Dart forth againe thoſe comfortable beames,</l>
               <l>To dry theſe ſtreames, which drowned haue my reſt,</l>
               <l>A ſmall requeſt, is one relenting looke.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. IIII.</head>
               <l>WHere in the Store-houſe of the heau'ns, was found</l>
               <l>The goodly ſampler, whereout nature wrought,</l>
               <l>That faire embraudrie, which exceeds mans thought,</l>
               <l>As farre, as doe the ſtarres our retch from ground.</l>
               <l>Faire <hi>Lada,</hi> whoſe rare beautie ſo renownd,</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Ioue,</hi> from his celeſtiall ſeat downe brought,</l>
               <l>When he the Warders of that treaſure ſought,</l>
               <l>To tempt with ſhowres of gold as bookes reſownd.</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Daphue,</hi> in her huntereſſe aray,</l>
               <l>Walking the woods, the day that <hi>Phoebus</hi> chaſt her,</l>
               <l>Could euer threds of ſo pure gould diſplay,</l>
               <l>Nor ſuch vnſpotted mynes of Alabaſter.</l>
               <l>And were her heart conforme to her complexion,</l>
               <l>Our earth had not enuyed the heau'ns perfection.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:4"/>
               <head>Sonet. V.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CYnthia,</hi> the time will come, when looking backe,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt behold how time hath tryed my truth:</l>
               <l>And proudly tryumph'd in thy beauties wracke:</l>
               <l>(Too late for both of vs,) thou wile haue ruth,</l>
               <l>And grieue, that thou diddeſt not in time betake</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe, to that, from which thou now ſo ſwarueſt:</l>
               <l>When blaſts of age, thy youthes faire fields doe ſhake,</l>
               <l>Which were not reap'd in ſeaſon of their harueſt.</l>
               <l>Regard (deere Mayd) my right, ſo plainely ſhow'd,</l>
               <l>In theſe my writings, by thy name adorned,</l>
               <l>And thinke thy blooming youth, there beſt beſtow'd</l>
               <l>Where thy declyning age, ſhall leaſt be ſcorned.</l>
               <l>"So harmes foreſeene are better ſtill preuented</l>
               <l>"Than by experience of the loſſe repented.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. VI.</head>
               <l>LOng haue I ſought (ô ruthleſſe faire) to ſcale</l>
               <l>The long reſiſting walles of thy diſdaine:</l>
               <l>Th'aſſaulters, were ſighes, teares, and viſage pale,</l>
               <l>Which outwardly, bewrayd mine inward paine.</l>
               <l>Defire, conueyd this ruth-deſeruing rout,</l>
               <l>Vnto the fort, where my beſt hopes are ſeated,</l>
               <l>But then thy threatning frownes ſtraight ſallyed out,</l>
               <l>And with their might the weaker force defeated,</l>
               <l>Yet loth thus recreant to forſake the field,</l>
               <l>Behold, how fairely to compound I proffer,</l>
               <l>Chooſe thy conditions as thou liſt, and yeeld,</l>
               <l>And for reward, ſee here what I doe offer,</l>
               <l>The pureſt loue, that euer heart did hold,</l>
               <l>More worth than Mountaines of the <hi>Indian</hi> gold.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:4"/>
               <head>Sonet. VII.</head>
               <l>HEre <hi>Cynthia</hi> at thy feet I humbly tender,</l>
               <l>The keyes of my (till now) vnconquered heart,</l>
               <l>Whence I ſue forth, voyd of affected art,</l>
               <l>Sighes, teares, and prayers, to make my ſoules ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render.</l>
               <l>Thou art a woman, women ſhould be tender,</l>
               <l>Shew by thy ſentence, of what ſex thou art,</l>
               <l>And let their humble ſutes, preuaile in part,</l>
               <l>That plead not, for an obſtinate offender.</l>
               <l>All, ſeeke to breake thy breſts congealed Ice,</l>
               <l>But ſo hard is thy heart, that nothing mooues thee,</l>
               <l>Ah, leaue deere Loue, to be hene eforth ſo rice,</l>
               <l>The onely fault, for which the world reprooues thee,</l>
               <l>And weigh not lightly ſo, his ſound aduice,</l>
               <l>That with ſuch faith, ſuch truth, ſuch feruor loues thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. VIII.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CYuthia,</hi> the teares which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine eies down flowing,</l>
               <l>Did repreſent the Spring-tides of my ſorrow.</l>
               <l>Are now quite ſpent, eu'n when my cares new grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</l>
               <l>Had greateſt need, their further aid to borrow;</l>
               <l>My voice, which had in charge, my teates to ſecond,</l>
               <l>Is with inceſſant cries, grow'n hoarſe, and broken,</l>
               <l>For now foure gloomie Winters hath it reckon'd,</l>
               <l>Since of my loue, to thee it firſt had ſpoken;</l>
               <l>Then, ſince my teares, and voice, at once are reft me,</l>
               <l>View in my face, the dumbe ſhewes of my greefe,</l>
               <l>Read in theſe lines, which onely now are left me,</l>
               <l>Legions of woes, raunged in words ſo briefe,</l>
               <l>Sure they would moue thee, if thou once did'ſt know them,</l>
               <l>But ah, they are ſo great I cannot ſhowe them.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:5"/>
               <head>Sonet. IX.</head>
               <l>OFt haue I wiſhed, in my zeales exceſſe,</l>
               <l>To make my <hi>Cynthia</hi> ſee proofes of my dutie,</l>
               <l>That in theſe lines, I could as well expreſſe,</l>
               <l>As in my ſoule, I doe admire her beautie,</l>
               <l>Or that great <hi>Daniell,</hi> fit for ſuch a taske,</l>
               <l>This wonder of our Iſle, had ſeene, and heeded,</l>
               <l>Then ſhould his glorious muſe, her worth vnmaske,</l>
               <l>And he himſelfe, himſelfe ſhould haue exceeded;</l>
               <l>Then England, Fraunce, Spaine, Greece, and Italye,</l>
               <l>And all that th'Ocean from our ſhoares diuideth,</l>
               <l>Would ouer-runne their bounds, and hether flye,</l>
               <l>To finde the treaſure, that our Ireland hideth,</l>
               <l>But beſt is, that we neuer doe diſcloſe it,</l>
               <l>Since knowne but of our ſelues, we ſhall not loſe it.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. X.</head>
               <l>TO thee, the Lodeſtone of my heauie thought,</l>
               <l>To thee, the Starre that guides my beaten barke,</l>
               <l>To thee, the faireſt one that nature wrought,</l>
               <l>To thee, that art the worlds admired marke,</l>
               <l>I ſend theſe mournfull hymnes, my zeale hath brought,</l>
               <l>From out my lightleſſe griefes, <hi>Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erian</hi> darke,</l>
               <l>And from diſpaires deepe gulfe, that long hath ſought,</l>
               <l>To drowne thy glorious praiſe, in my liues Arke.</l>
               <l>Appeaſe, (ô louely Mayd) this raging ſtorme,</l>
               <l>With thy ſweet ſmiles, to me more comfortable,</l>
               <l>Than his <hi>Ermoes,</hi> to the Sea-mane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies.</l>
               <l>What though mine artleſſe lines want phraſe, and forme,</l>
               <l>Thy fauours, may their lowlineſſe enable,</l>
               <l>To lift thy ſacred name aboue the skies.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:5"/>
               <head>Sonet. XI.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pid,</hi> that vnder thy ſweet Yoke haſt brought,</l>
               <l>Th'inhabitants, of this huge globe around,</l>
               <l>And that the depth of my deſires, do'ſt ſound,</l>
               <l>And ſeeſt the ſecrets, of mine inward thought,</l>
               <l>Thou ſeeſt, I feele, how deerely I haue bought,</l>
               <l>My wayting on thy ſtanderd ſo renownd,</l>
               <l>And yet thou leau'ſt me groueling on the grownd,</l>
               <l>By long delayes, now tir'd and ouer wrought;</l>
               <l>I ſee, but too farre off, that lamping light,</l>
               <l>To which thou doeſt me driue, and ſpurre amaine,</l>
               <l>But lo, I want thy wings, to make my flight;</l>
               <l>Enough, and more, doe my deſires obtaine,</l>
               <l>If I may waſt, in my deſires by leyſer,</l>
               <l>And that my ſighes, and teares, do not diſpleaſe her.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. XII.</head>
               <l>I ſaw in earth, a forme Angelicall,</l>
               <l>And heau'nly graces, in a worldly wight,</l>
               <l>Which did my ſoule ſo rauiſh and delight,</l>
               <l>That ſince her name, I celebrate and call.</l>
               <l>I ſawe from her faire eies, the teares downe fall,</l>
               <l>Thoſe eyes which oft haue dim'd the Sunnes cleare light,</l>
               <l>And heard her ſighing, vtter words of might,</l>
               <l>To ſtay the flouds, and moue the mountains tall.</l>
               <l>Doole, pittie, anger worthineſſe, and loue,</l>
               <l>So ſweete a mourning melodie conſorted,</l>
               <l>That thither woods, and hils, and rockes remoue,</l>
               <l>And dead mens bones, out of their graue reſorted.</l>
               <l>The ſpheares and ſtarres, did ſtray from their due courſe,</l>
               <l>ſuch of this heau'nly muſicke was the force.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:6"/>
               <head>Sonet. XIII.</head>
               <l>MIne eies how can you without dazeling view,</l>
               <l>The faireſt hew that euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie had ſeene?</l>
               <l>That ſouereigne Queen whom your ſad looks haue ſewd?</l>
               <l>No Sunne hath vewd, nor neuer ſhall her peere:</l>
               <l>O you more cleare then are the ſunnes cleare beames.</l>
               <l>Receiue theſe ſtreames the tribute of mine eies.</l>
               <l>And you my cries the orators of ſadneſſe,</l>
               <l>Turning my gladneſſe into ruthfull moanes,</l>
               <l>Ioyne with my groanes, blacke regiſters of ſorrow,</l>
               <l>And ſad words borrow of my dolefull tongue,</l>
               <l>To tell the wrong that you bereeues your food,</l>
               <l>Then what ſowre moode, can moue her to withſtand you.</l>
               <l>So fairly land you, in that happie port,</l>
               <l>Where doth reſort the prize for which ye venter:</l>
               <l>And lowly enter to complaine my griefe,</l>
               <l>To my ſoules theefe, my liues Iudge now ordained.</l>
               <l>Let mine vnfeigned faith preuaile, deare iewell,</l>
               <l>O be not cruell ſince thou art ſo faire.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. XIIII.</head>
               <l>O Be not cruell, ſince thou art ſo faire,</l>
               <l>Let not diſdaine my high deſerts diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Nor one foule fault thy beauties prize impaire,</l>
               <l>Sweete thoughts do beſt beſeeme ſo ſweete a face.</l>
               <l>Behold the triple region of the aire,</l>
               <l>Woods, valleys, mountaines, rocks, and euerie place,</l>
               <l>Are filled with Ecchoes of my plaints and prayer,</l>
               <l>Which at thy de affened eares, ſtill ſue for grace.</l>
               <l>All of them ſhew each in his diuerſe kind,</l>
               <l>That of my wofull caſe they haue compaſſion,</l>
               <l>The ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks my words repeating, ſeeme enclin'd</l>
               <l>To beare ſome burden of my hidden paſſion,</l>
               <l>Ah <hi>Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thia</hi> heare at length my grieuous mones,</l>
               <l>And be not harder than theſe ſenceleſſe ſtones.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:6"/>
               <head>Sonet. XV.</head>
               <l>WHen careful thoughts that long diſturb'd my mind</l>
               <l>Had giu'n my wearie ſences leaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt,</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Morph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> aroſe as beetle blinde,</l>
               <l>And did with his blacke Mace, mine eyes arreſt,</l>
               <l>Me thought I ſaw a louely milke-white Hind,</l>
               <l>Whom ſtraight purſued a ſtately Hart, whoſe creſt,</l>
               <l>Did well declare be was of noble kind,</l>
               <l>And fawning ſhew'd he lou'd the gentle beaſt:</l>
               <l>Then forthwith did a mongrell whelpe appeare,</l>
               <l>His Sire a Stag, but on a Roe begotten,</l>
               <l>And ſoone this noble Hart beheld his deare,</l>
               <l>Accept th'vnkindly beaſt, himſelfe forgotten.</l>
               <l>Who thence-forth euer raung'd the fields alone,</l>
               <l>And to the woods and winds ſtill made his mone.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. XVI.</head>
               <l>VNto the woods and winds he made his mone,</l>
               <l>And ſure his dolefull caſe I greatly rued,</l>
               <l>But that my mind was call'd from thence anone,</l>
               <l>To heed as ſtrange a ſight that ſtraight enſued.</l>
               <l>Me thought two gentle Hawkes, but ioind in one,</l>
               <l>By kind and kindly choice, aloft I viewd:</l>
               <l>When lo, I ſaw the female, ſoard and gone.</l>
               <l>After a keſtrell Kite obſcurely mewd:</l>
               <l>Which ſight ſo ſore my fantaſie did vexe,</l>
               <l>That ſuddenly I ſtart out of my ſlumber:</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thia,</hi> but the frailtie of her ſexe,</l>
               <l>Doth me with ſad ſuſpect and feares encumber:</l>
               <l>But cre my deere, my Hawke, make ſuch a flight,</l>
               <l>O let theſe eyes firſt want their wonted light.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:7"/>
               <head>Sonet. XVII.</head>
               <l>O Let theſe eies, firſt want their woonted light,</l>
               <l>And vgly death, my captiue corps immure,</l>
               <l>And day be cancel'd by eternall night,</l>
               <l>And no Sun-ſhine, nor Moone, ne ſtars endure,</l>
               <l>Ere the worlds wonder, and my ſoules delight,</l>
               <l>Which doth the ſtarres downe from their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates allure,</l>
               <l>To yeeld their homage to her beautie bright,</l>
               <l>ſhould her faire worthes, with ſo foule ſtaines obſcure,</l>
               <l>Ere I, who blav'd her name in forraine ſoiles,</l>
               <l>Making old <hi>Albion</hi> ſhores her praiſe reſound,</l>
               <l>Should ſee a ſtranger, triumph in my ſpoiles,</l>
               <l>Or any elſe, with my freſh garland crown'd.</l>
               <l>No, no, thoſe Planets that her birth allotted,</l>
               <l>Will neuer ſee, their glories glaſſe ſo ſpotted.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. XVIII.</head>
               <l>O Diſmald dreames, ofſpring of ſleepe and night,</l>
               <l>Hels meſſenger, fore-telling our misfortune,</l>
               <l>Robbers of reſt, and enemies of light,</l>
               <l>That ſtill with haſtie ſights our ſence importune.</l>
               <l>Could not my <hi>Genius</hi> ill affected ſpright,</l>
               <l>Contriue the ruine of my weake eſtate,</l>
               <l>But you, O curſed dreames, for more deſpight,</l>
               <l>Muſt before time, mine ill prognoſticate?</l>
               <l>And thou, that haſt my loue ſo meanly prized,</l>
               <l>The hire thereof vnto a ſtraunger giuing,</l>
               <l>Was it for this, I thee haue canonized</l>
               <l>A heauenly Saint, though here on earth yet liuing.</l>
               <l>Ay me, what croſſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urious ſtarre aſſign'd</l>
               <l>So faire a face, to ſuch a faithleſſe mind.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:7"/>
               <head>Sonet. XIX.</head>
               <l>LIke as the ſiluer ſwanne in her extreames,</l>
               <l>Be-mones her ſelfe, with doolefull harmonie,</l>
               <l>And takes her laſtleaue, of her haunted ſtreames,</l>
               <l>Aſſuring them, that now her death drawes ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>So thou my Muſe, breath out in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>The ſad diſcourſes of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</l>
               <l>And let thy lines, yelad in mourning co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</l>
               <l>My neere approching end, prognoſticare;</l>
               <l>And thou poore heart, ſometime the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſefull bowre,</l>
               <l>Where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouely <hi>Cynthia,</hi> deigned to repoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er,</l>
               <l>Thy ioyfull tunes, change into wailing ſowre,</l>
               <l>For now thy ioy is paſt, and thou muſt looſe her.</l>
               <l>Yet with thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>racke, procure in her ſome ruth,</l>
               <l>And make the world admire ſuch loue and truth.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="madrigal">
               <head>The firſt Madrigall.</head>
               <l>HAppie the beautious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owres, and berbars ſoote,</l>
               <l>Wherein my <hi>Cynthia</hi> with the Muſes walkes,</l>
               <l>Happie the ſhore, that heares her as ſhe talkes,</l>
               <l>And beares t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mpreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, of her daintie foote:</l>
               <l>Happie the groue, which her aſpect doth grace,</l>
               <l>Happie the lake, wherein ſhe bathes her f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</l>
               <l>Happie the ſoile, ordain'd to be her place.</l>
               <l>Soile, lake groue, flowers, to eaſe my deepe diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Impart ſome part, of your great happineſſe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="madrigal">
               <head>Madrigall. II.</head>
               <l>THe wounded deare from running neuer ceaſeth,</l>
               <l>Spur'd by the piercing ſhaft within his ſide,</l>
               <l>His grieuous paine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doth him ſtill forward guide,</l>
               <l>And ſtill his reſtleſſe race, his paine increaſeth.</l>
               <l>Right ſo fare I, with that ſame deadly dart,</l>
               <l>Where with fierce loue, hath pierc'd my conquer'd hart,</l>
               <l>The more I fice, the more my wound doth ſmart.</l>
               <l>And now I find, in vaine they flee or tarrie,</l>
               <l>That with themſelues, heir owne deſtruction carrie.</l>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:8"/>
               <l>That hath me, fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d ay me of feeling earth,</l>
               <l>And curſe the day when firſt I ſaw that Sunne.</l>
               <l>Which makes me looke like one nurſt in the wood,</l>
               <l>So fierce a Tygre in the wildeſt wood,</l>
               <l>Did neuer feed, as yet by night ne day,</l>
               <l>As ſhee for whom I weepe by ſhade and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</l>
               <l>Gaining no truce from teares at eu'n ne morne:</l>
               <l>And though my ſelfe be made of loweſt earth,</l>
               <l>My high deſires come from the loftie ſtarres,</l>
               <l>O that ere I returne to you faire ſtarres,</l>
               <l>Or to my wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed walkes within the wood,</l>
               <l>Tyring this corps which ſoone will turne to earth,</l>
               <l>I ſaw her rue me, who may in one day,</l>
               <l>Repaire my foure yeares loſſe, and ere the morne,</l>
               <l>Earich me at the riſing of the Sunne.</l>
               <l>That I were with her at the ſet of Sunne,</l>
               <l>And none beheld vs ſaue the ſilent flarres,</l>
               <l>One night that could be ſhortned by no morne,</l>
               <l>And that ſhe might not turne into greene wood,</l>
               <l>To leaue mine armes as <hi>Daphne</hi> did that day,</l>
               <l>That golden <hi>Phoebus</hi> chaſ'd her here on earth.</l>
               <l>But firſt ſhall earth encloſe me in the wood,</l>
               <l>And dayes gray cope embrodered be with ſtarres,</l>
               <l>Before my Sunne enioy ſo ſweet a morne.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:8"/>
            <head>The ſecond part.</head>
            <div n="1" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. I.</head>
               <l>STep forth into the world mine Orphane verſe,</l>
               <l>Abortiue brood, of my deceaſed hopes,</l>
               <l>And doolefully, purſue your parents hearſe,</l>
               <l>Attir'd in your blacke ſtoales, and tawnie copes,</l>
               <l>Such mourning weedes, beſeemes our mournfull woes,</l>
               <l>And ſith reuenge, is all your remedie,</l>
               <l>With out-cries loud, to coaſts vnknowne diſcloſe,</l>
               <l>The dire contriuer of my tragidie:</l>
               <l>Then propheſie, with holie furie fir'd,</l>
               <l>And tell faire <hi>Cynthia,</hi> how the heau'ns on hie,</l>
               <l>The ſunne, the ſtarres, the earth haue all conſpir'd,</l>
               <l>To wreake my wrongs, and end her tyrannie:</l>
               <l>And that the ſprights below, and powr's aboue her,</l>
               <l>Threaten reuenge, for murther of her louer.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. II.</head>
               <l>LEd by the fainting ſteps of forlorne hope,</l>
               <l>Onward I go, where froward fates me driue,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll paſt the bounds, of this our Horoſcope,</l>
               <l>With wearied lims, at laſt I did arriue,</l>
               <l>Within a deſeit darke vnhaunted caue,</l>
               <l>So low, that loath'd it ſeem'd of worlds pure aire,</l>
               <l>And by the Poeſies, on the poſts ygraue,</l>
               <l>I found it was the manſion of diſpaire;</l>
               <l>Further I paſt, vnto an inner roome,</l>
               <l>Where that ſad wight, ſat croſſe-leg'd in his chaire,</l>
               <l>And humbly pray'd him to vnfold his doome,</l>
               <l>If any bliſſe, my bale ſhould aye repaire;</l>
               <l>Die wretch quoth he, and leaue not Fortunes ſcorne,</l>
               <l>thy hap was buried, ere thy hopes were borne.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:9"/>
               <head>Sonet. III.</head>
               <l>FAire trees, in whoſe ſmooth rines I oft engrau'd,</l>
               <l>That name, which loue had in my heart enrold,</l>
               <l>To whom as in thoſe burning fits I rau'd,</l>
               <l>My neuer ceaſing paines at large I told.</l>
               <l>Cleare lake, whoſe calme vaſt floore I ouer-pau'd</l>
               <l>With teares, that from my fertile eyes downe rol'd,</l>
               <l>When of your waters oft I humbly crau'd.</l>
               <l>To caſe my flaming bowels with their cold:</l>
               <l>Declare my foure yeares loue, my diſcontents,</l>
               <l>And how I haue at <hi>Cynthiaes</hi> hand deſerued,</l>
               <l>And you tall trees, my loues true monuments,</l>
               <l>Retaine thoſe lines, which in your coates I carued,</l>
               <l>That men her name may read and reading hate,</l>
               <l>That was in loue ſo falſe, and ſo ingrate.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. IIII.</head>
               <l>O That my loue were with thy liking ended,</l>
               <l>And with thy faith, my fire had alſo turned,</l>
               <l>thy fault ſhould not thus ſtill be reprehended,</l>
               <l>And few had know'n the flame wherein I burned:</l>
               <l>My free-borne rimes, that ah too long haue mourned,</l>
               <l>And from blacke <hi>Lethes</hi> gulfe, thy name defended,</l>
               <l>Should of their charge, thy praiſe be now disburdned.</l>
               <l>And thou remaine vnknow'n, and vncommended:</l>
               <l>But ſince my cruell ſtarres decrees are ſuch,</l>
               <l>As cauſe me loue, and proſecute my death,</l>
               <l>My conſtant end, ſhall trie my loues pure tuch,</l>
               <l>Yeelding the farewell of my failing breath,</l>
               <l>To thee, O Vulture on my heart-ſtrings ſeaſing,</l>
               <l>Sith that my death is moſt vnto thy pleaſing.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:9"/>
               <head>Sonet. V.</head>
               <l>MAruell not <hi>Cynthia,</hi> that my muſe brings forth,</l>
               <l>theſe bitter fruits of long conceal'd diſdaigne,</l>
               <l>Seeking to taint, thy neuer-matched worth,</l>
               <l>With oft obiecting thine vnkindneſſe ſtaine,</l>
               <l>For all, are rauings of a feeble braine,</l>
               <l>Of one, whom loue, and hate, haue long held ſicke,</l>
               <l>Who, weakened by the force of former paine,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Cynthiaes</hi> change, is wexen lunatike.</l>
               <l>Thou <hi>Cynthia,</hi> art the Moone whoſe influence,</l>
               <l>the flowing tides of mine affects doth ſunder,</l>
               <l>whoſe faire aſpect, food of my greedie ſence,</l>
               <l>Now hauing loſt, I ſterue, nor is it wonder,</l>
               <l>that my ſoules pow'rs, thus from their Cels haue ranged,</l>
               <l>Sith thou thy faith, but not thy forme, haſt changed,</l>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. VI.</head>
               <l>AY me, diſpaire comes now to claime the ſcope,</l>
               <l>Of my ſad thoughts drownd in deepe woes exceſſe,</l>
               <l>For I am reft, the obiect of my hope,</l>
               <l>And my fierce faire, a ſtranger doth poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Sydneys</hi> gentle ſheepheard could deuiſe,</l>
               <l>In ſuch a caſe, to find a remedie,</l>
               <l>who blear'd his icalous hoſts miſtruſtfull eyes,</l>
               <l>By his kind hoſteſſe handſome induſtrie,</l>
               <l>Then why ſhould I deſpaire, of like ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>whoſe happie riuall, is a harmeleſſe boy,</l>
               <l>But ah, my <hi>Cynthia</hi> doth this hope ſuppreſſe,</l>
               <l>who chaſtely proud perſiſts, and ſweetly coy,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Cynthia,</hi> why do I for this reproue thee,</l>
               <l>Since for thou waſt ſo chaſt, I firſt did loue thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:10"/>
               <head>Sonet. VII.</head>
               <l>THe peerleſſe bird, bred in the <hi>Arabian</hi> ſoile,</l>
               <l>that ſolely liues on earth, without a mate,</l>
               <l>Strangely prouides by his owne ſmall ſpoile,</l>
               <l>An heire, that may ſucceed him in his ſtate:</l>
               <l>For when he knoweth his houre, he mounts ſo hie,</l>
               <l>that kindled by the ſunne, in flames he flaſhes,</l>
               <l>and in that inſtant, out begins to flie</l>
               <l>an other of his kinde, borne of his aſhes.</l>
               <l>Eu'n ſo my heart, conſum'd with raging fire.</l>
               <l>Dies <hi>(Cynthia)</hi> that thy will may be fulfilled,</l>
               <l>But ſtraight, loue charmes it with more freſh deſires,</l>
               <l>and ſo reuiues, what thy diſdeigne erſt killed:</l>
               <l>Thus, doeſt thou kill, and cure againe, O cruell,</l>
               <l>Becauſe my flames, may neuer want their fuell.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. VIII.</head>
               <l>Thoſe ſcalding fighes, which ſhew'd my harts chaſt fire,</l>
               <l>More hot then ſunne-beames, in the midſt of Iulie,</l>
               <l>Nor thoſe warme teares, ſprung from more warme deſires,</l>
               <l>that on my ruthleſſe loue, did wait ſo duly;</l>
               <l>Could vnto that ſupreame reward aſpire,</l>
               <l>an infant late hath got, ſtart vp but newly,</l>
               <l>Whoſe birth, or owne deſert, was nothing hier,</l>
               <l>Ne could his age, yet learne to loue ſo truly.</l>
               <l>Yet, though I ſee, my ſelfe thus made a ſcoffe,</l>
               <l>I can not ſtoppe the courſe, of my zeales flood,</l>
               <l>My loue, and truth, when hopes are all cut off,</l>
               <l>Shall grow, like impes, which from hew'n ſtumps do bud,</l>
               <l>the world ſhall ſee, when nought my hope doth nouriſh,</l>
               <l>My faith once vow'd amidſt deſpaire can flouriſh.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:10"/>
               <head>Sonet. IX.</head>
               <l>OH whither runſt thou thus, mine angry pen?</l>
               <l>Whither, my bitter, and reſpectleſſe times?</l>
               <l>Gainſt her, who makes you loue in after times,</l>
               <l>and ſummons you, from out dumbe ſilence den.</l>
               <l>O, how I ſhame the world abroad ſhould ken,</l>
               <l>Your railing Satires hates harſh ſounding chimes,</l>
               <l>So falſly charging, with iniurious crimes,</l>
               <l>the worlds chiefe wonder, glorie vnto men.</l>
               <l>My ſoule, the pray to tyrannizing loue,</l>
               <l>found the retreat to mine inuectiue Muſe;</l>
               <l>Who, though my ruthleſſe faire, thou canſt not moue,</l>
               <l>Muſt yet obey thy fate, which ſends the newes,</l>
               <l>that when my bones, in earth are cold and rotten,</l>
               <l>thy flame ſhall not be quencht, nor loue forgotten.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. X.</head>
               <l>CEaſe mournfull Muſe, thine vnregarded mones,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat with my griefe, encreaſe my loues diſdaigne:</l>
               <l>Diſdaigne more hard to breake, then marble ſtones,</l>
               <l>For thoſe, are pierc'd with drops of ſofteſt raine:</l>
               <l>But I, that from mine eyes, ſuch ſhowres do raigne,</l>
               <l>to mollifie a heart, more hard then ſtones,</l>
               <l>Find for my laſt reliefe, but ſterne diſdaigne,</l>
               <l>Which ſutes my new-born griefs, with new found mones.</l>
               <l>Since then ſuch griefe, clad in ſuch artleſſe truth</l>
               <l>In my remorſeleſſe faire no pittie ſturres,</l>
               <l>Since my complaints which muſt procure ſome ruth,</l>
               <l>In ſtrangers eares, do ſound ſo harſh in hurs:</l>
               <l>Ile ſilent die, and leaue to deathes recitall,</l>
               <l>The ſtorie of my loue, and loues requitall.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="canzone">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:11"/>
               <head>Canzone.</head>
               <l>THe ruler of this mightie Monarchie,</l>
               <l>That in his thought, this triple frame ſuſtaines,</l>
               <l>Ruling it after his diuine election,</l>
               <l>Commaunded once the heau'ns, and ſtarres on hie,</l>
               <l>And Elements to ioyne their pow're and paines,</l>
               <l>To build a worke of exquiſite perfection;</l>
               <l>They ſtraight, their Lords direction,</l>
               <l>Obey, with care and dutious diligence,</l>
               <l>In ſuch obedient ſtrife, they all contended,</l>
               <l>That ſoone the worke was ended:</l>
               <l>So ſtately, faire, and of ſuch excellence,</l>
               <l>As earſt was neuer ſeene, of mortall ſenſe.</l>
               <l>The walles were built, of ſpotleſſe Alabaſter,</l>
               <l>The roofe, where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the owner ſeemed lauiſh,</l>
               <l>Was all thicke couer'd, with the pureſt gold,</l>
               <l>Saue onely that the front, white ſnow did plaiſter,</l>
               <l>The loftie windowes, that my ſoule did rauiſh,</l>
               <l>With deare delight, as I did them behold,</l>
               <l>(Ay me that was ſo bold)</l>
               <l>Were two blacke orbes, encloz'd in circlesblew,</l>
               <l>Of let, and Saphire, quaintly interlaced,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Hebene</hi> Arkes imbraced,</l>
               <l>Whence forth in troupes, Loues winged ſouldiers flew.</l>
               <l>And tooke me, ere I could their waites eſchew,</l>
               <l>The gate was built of ſnow-white Iuorie,</l>
               <l>All drawne in compaſſe curiouſly about,</l>
               <l>And eu'nly ſet, within pure Corall bounds;</l>
               <l>the leaues were brazill of Vermilion die:</l>
               <l>Within a Porter ſate, who ſtill ſent out,</l>
               <l>A heau'nly conſort, of melodious ſounds,</l>
               <l>Which gaue me many wounds,</l>
               <l>And cured them eft, with <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> of ioyes,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:11"/>
               <l>Not <hi>Orphens</hi> ſong, ne Mermaids muſicke rare,</l>
               <l>Could euer yet compare</l>
               <l>With this delightfull, ſtrange, melodious noyſe,</l>
               <l>Which ends and breeds a new, mine oldaunoyes.</l>
               <l>Amid the hall, there was a ſtately ſeate,</l>
               <l>With curious skill, and skilfull care yearued,</l>
               <l>A ſquared ſtone, of orient Diamond:</l>
               <l>Here reaſon ſate, and great affaires did treat,</l>
               <l>And with his lore, this peereleſſe worke preſerued,</l>
               <l>Preſcribing lawes, vnto that happie land,</l>
               <l>Loue walked on the ſtrand,</l>
               <l>For this faire pile is walled with faireſt riuers,</l>
               <l>And when he had eſpied the pleaſing marke,</l>
               <l>He ſtraight did bend his Arke,</l>
               <l>And at the precious Chaire, he ſhot whole quiuers,</l>
               <l>But ay the ſtone return'd his ſhafts in ſhiners.</l>
               <l>When thus a while in vaine his force he tri'd,</l>
               <l>Scorning the ſhamefull foile, he wheeles about,</l>
               <l>T'awreake his ſpite, vpon ſome weaker pow'r:</l>
               <l>And me vnarm'd alas he firſt eſpi'd,</l>
               <l>As I ſtood wareleſſe gazing in the rout,</l>
               <l>Which came to wonder, at this goodly towre.</l>
               <l>He ſtar'd with viſage ſowre,</l>
               <l>And from his quiuer tooke a golden flight,</l>
               <l>That from the reſt, of purpoſe he ſelected,</l>
               <l>And when I leaſt ſuſpected,</l>
               <l>I felt the ſhaft full in my boſome light,</l>
               <l>And yeeld I muſt, that wanted force to fight.</l>
               <l>Like one that hauing a repulſe ſuſtain'd,</l>
               <l>aſſaulting of a fort, doth turne his way,</l>
               <l>and ſacks ſome village weake, and vnprepar'd:</l>
               <l>Or like a Lion fierce, with famine ſhaign'd,</l>
               <l>who, when he failes of his deſired pray,</l>
               <l>Deuoures the beaſts which he before had ſpar'd:</l>
               <l>So loue with me hath far'd:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:12"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy power which carſt did vanquiſh,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus,</hi> thundring <hi>Ione,</hi> and warlike <hi>Mars,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Be not decayd and ſcarce:</l>
               <l>With thoſe bright armes, that cauſe me thus to languiſh,</l>
               <l>Reuenge thine owne reproch, and caſe mine anguiſh.</l>
               <l>My ſong if any ſeeke,</l>
               <l>By their prompt wits thy myſteries to meaſure,</l>
               <l>Let them diuine, but neuer know thy treaſure.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="madrigal">
               <head>Madrigall. I.</head>
               <l>I Saw my faire, abrode the fields once randoning,</l>
               <l>That faire, on whom the heau'ns their graces lauiſhed,</l>
               <l>Like louely <hi>Thetis,</hi> her ſea-bowres abandoning,</l>
               <l>My ſprights, forthwith with deepe delight were rauiſhed,</l>
               <l>But then, on me ſhe caſt her looke ſo ſcornfully,</l>
               <l>That downe I ſunke, and ſhe nought caring vaniſhed;</l>
               <l>And euer ſince, I waile thus mournfully:</l>
               <l>From my ſoules bliſſe, by this dumbe ſentence baniſhed:</l>
               <l>Then iudge the world, how well my loue is guerdoned,</l>
               <l>Where I for meed, requeſt but to be pardoned.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="madrigal">
               <head>Madrigall. II.</head>
               <l>THe burning lampe, when once that oyle is ſpent,</l>
               <l>Whoſe humour erſt, preſeru'd it in his prime,</l>
               <l>Leeſeth his light, and dieth incontinent;</l>
               <l>So I, whom falſhood and vnkindneſſe rife,</l>
               <l>Haue left depri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d of her who was ſometime,</l>
               <l>Oile of my flaming lampe, lampe of my light,</l>
               <l>Do bid my laſt adue, to woddly ioyes.</l>
               <l>Which I (God wot) haue not enioy'd but ſeldome,</l>
               <l>For now mine end will end all mine annoyes,</l>
               <l>And to a lothſome life faire death is welcome.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:12"/>
               <head>Sonet. XI.</head>
               <l>FAre-well ſweete Iſle, within whoſe pleaſant Bowres,</l>
               <l>I firſt receiued life, and huing ayre,</l>
               <l>Fare-well the ſoile, where grew thoſe heau'nly flowres,</l>
               <l>which brauely de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke the face of my fierce faire,</l>
               <l>Fare-well the place, whence I beheld the towres,</l>
               <l>with pale aſpect, where her I ſaw repaire:</l>
               <l>Fare-well ye floods, encreaſed by thoſe ſhowres,</l>
               <l>wherewith mine eyes, did entertaine deſpaire:</l>
               <l>Fare-well cleare lake, which of art made the glaſſe,</l>
               <l>to rareſt beautie, of mine ill the roote,</l>
               <l>when ſhe vouchſafes vpon thy ſhores to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Bleſſing thy happie ſand, with thy faire foote,</l>
               <l>Fare-well faire <hi>Cynthia,</hi> whoſe vnkind conſent,</l>
               <l>Hath caus'd mine euerlaſting baniſhment.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="sonnet">
               <head>Sonet. XII.</head>
               <l>YOu that peruſe theſe ſorrow charming rimes,</l>
               <l>the dolefull ditties of a dying ſpright.</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to rue my ruth-deſeruing plight,</l>
               <l>and know the treaſure of your happie times.</l>
               <l>No glorie I affect of future times:</l>
               <l>Such honours are too high for my poore plight,</l>
               <l>Striue they for ſuch, whoſe vnaffected ſpright,</l>
               <l>Forge them a ſubiect, to ſet forth their rimes.</l>
               <l>If any chaunce: to find in theſe my times,</l>
               <l>the liuely patterne of his deadly plight,</l>
               <l>Let him condole with mine afflicted ſpright,</l>
               <l>whoſe griefe may not be told, in length of times.</l>
               <l>Times are to ſo ſhort to ſhew my wofull plight,</l>
               <l>No rymes can ſound the ſorrowes of my ſpright.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:13"/>
               <head>His leane taking of<hi>Cynthia,</hi> r. herein his owne death is preſaged.</head>
               <l>COmming to take my laſt leaue of my Loue,</l>
               <l>(Oh that I then leaue of my life had taken,)</l>
               <l>I told her, how I now my chance would proue:</l>
               <l>Abrode, ſince home-borne hopes had me forſaken.</l>
               <l>She then, in whom my piercing griefe did waken,</l>
               <l>Some ſparke of ruth, too late alas aſſayes,</l>
               <l>To croſſe this courſe, which I had vndertaken,</l>
               <l>Now ſhe perſwades, now weepes, now ſweetly prayes.</l>
               <l>But, neither reaſons, teares, nor prayers, could raiſe</l>
               <l>The ſiege, that honour to my heart had layd,</l>
               <l>When with a deep-fetcht ſigh, the louely Maid,</l>
               <l>The horror of her breaſt, thus out bewrayes:</l>
               <l>Wo worth, quoth ſhe, muſt that deare head and hand,</l>
               <l>Lie lowly earthed, in an vncouth land.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>The third Part.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:10702:13"/>
            <div n="1" type="sonnet">
               <head>To his Coſin Masſter Richard Nugen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Donower.</head>
               <head type="sub">Sonet. I.</head>
               <l>MIne owne <hi>Dicke Nugent,</hi> if thou liſt to know,</l>
               <l>The cauſe that makes me ſhun my weſterne home</l>
               <l>And how my tedious time, I here beſtow,</l>
               <l>Where angry <hi>Thetis,</hi> gainſt her bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds doth fome:</l>
               <l>Weet, that to eaſe that neuer-healing wound,</l>
               <l>Which now foure ſommers heate hath made to feſter,</l>
               <l>By time, by abſence, or by counſell ſound.</l>
               <l>I flee the ſoile, where my ſweete foe doth reſt her.</l>
               <l>I ſoiourne here, where I remaine ſo eaſde,</l>
               <l>By this my flight, of the tormenting blow;</l>
               <l>As doth the deare, on whom the ſhaft hath ſeazde,</l>
               <l>By late vnbending of the deadly bow;</l>
               <l>And ſince, I haue this curſle eu'n fatall proued,</l>
               <l>That I am borne to loue, and not be loued.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sonnet">
               <head>The anſwer of M. Richard Nugent of Donower.</head>
               <head type="sub">Sonet. II.</head>
               <l>MIne owne deare <hi>Dicke,</hi> whom I loue as my life,</l>
               <l>And euer ſhall, whiles I in life remaine,</l>
               <l>I thee aduiſe, to leaue this lingring ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Betweene thy loue, and thy loues hope ſo vaine,</l>
               <l>And for thoſe yeares, waſted ſo long in vaine,</l>
               <l>To ſhed ſome teares, with full remorſe of minde,</l>
               <l>And to be rid of thy tormenting paine,</l>
               <l>To ſhun the path, miſguided by the blind:</l>
               <l>As for to flee the place, of thy decay,</l>
               <l>I n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſlike, (if that may worke thine caſe.)</l>
               <l>Yet better were, this weed to roote away,</l>
               <l>Which ſo infects, and fils thee with diſeaſe:</l>
               <l>For luſt it is not loue, that doth torment,</l>
               <l>Where loue i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iuſt, there ſtill is found content.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:14"/>
               <head>A Reply to the former <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Sonet. III.</head>
               <l>DEare is my Loue to me, as is my life,</l>
               <l>And euer whiles I liue ſhall ſo remaine;</l>
               <l>Ne can preuaile a whit, thy friendly ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Seeking to ſtaunch my hearts loue-bleeding vaine.</l>
               <l>Leaue then (deare Friend) thy words to waſte in vaine,</l>
               <l>Which ſo renew, the affections of the minde,</l>
               <l>My minde that proudly glories in my paine,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it tels the world, I am not blinde.</l>
               <l>Ne can my Loue to thoſe faire eyes decay,</l>
               <l>Though their cleare beames, did firſt my ſoule diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>And rather will I ſtill thus pine away,</l>
               <l>Then ranſome with my loue, my loues hearts eaſe;</l>
               <l>Pure is the loue, which doth my life torment,</l>
               <l>My life ſo well beſtow'd, I die content.</l>
               <l>Blaſpheme no more, againſt my Loue ſo iuſt,</l>
               <l>Hearts truely louing, cannot thinke on luſt.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:14"/>
               <head>To his truſtie Friend Maister William Talbet.</head>
               <head type="sub">Sonet. IIII.</head>
               <l>NOwe will I write to ſatiſfie thy will,</l>
               <l>Yet what thou leaſt would read, that muſt I write;</l>
               <l>For <hi>Cynthia</hi> breathes the Theame into my quill,</l>
               <l>And what my hand layth downe, ſhee doth endite.</l>
               <l>My will ſaith ſhee (O Wretch) is that thou liue,</l>
               <l>And euer liue, in neuer-dying griefe,</l>
               <l>Hard dome, which ſo denyeth that Tyrants giue,</l>
               <l>To hapleſſe wretches, for their laſt reliefe.</l>
               <l>This Theame, I muſt delate and amplifie,</l>
               <l>With tragicke Stories, wrought by <hi>Fortunes</hi> ſpight,</l>
               <l>How with one fatall blade, both Louers dye,</l>
               <l>And of <hi>Leander</hi> drown'd in <hi>Heroes</hi> ſight.</l>
               <l>Thus of the dead, I ſad examples borowe,</l>
               <l>To furniſh out a Scene of liuing ſorrowe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faile not, my vowed ſeruice to commend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To that ſweete Lady, in whom vertue ſhines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whom leaſt I ſhould her iudgement graue offend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I <hi>leaue t'importune with myne idle Lines:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fare-well &amp; to thy trust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſelfe retaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe ſcenceleſſe rauings of a Loue-ſicke brayne.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:15"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Maſter William Talbet.</head>
               <head>Sonet. IIII.</head>
               <l>I Will giue thanks for this thy great good will,</l>
               <l>That bind'ſt thy ſelfe, at my requeſt to write,</l>
               <l>And well I like the ſubiect of thy quill,</l>
               <l>Which in thy name, my paſſions doth endite:</l>
               <l>Well thou deſcrib'ſt the ſtate wherein I liue,</l>
               <l>Nay how I the, in euer-liuing griefe:</l>
               <l>And though thy woes to mine, no helpe can giue,</l>
               <l>Yet fellowſhip to miſers is reliefe.</l>
               <l>Ioine then with me, thou need'ſt not amplifie,</l>
               <l>With aged tales thy wrong and Fortunes ſpite,</l>
               <l>Since of like wounds, we both at once muſt die,</l>
               <l>And both our harmes, procured by our ſight;</l>
               <l>Thou write we ſtill, and though thy lines I borrow,</l>
               <l>Yet be affir'd I need not learne thy ſorrow.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I neede not to that Ladie thee commend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With praiſe, who can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, where vertue ſhines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet did thine errand, hast I ſhould offend:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shee ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>il'd, peruſing of our careleſſe lines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſayd, write on, for if you ſhould retaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe idle humours, they would breake your brain.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="madrigal">
               <head>Maiſter Thomas Shol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> anſwer to the <hi>4.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drig all of the firſt part, which beginneth: <hi>Sweet are my</hi> Cynthiaes. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>WHat wight ſaw captiue ſtile ſo comfortable,</l>
               <l>As that, which thou didſt ſend to me this morne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:15"/>
               <l>Stile, that t'enchant the gods them ſelues were able,</l>
               <l>O that ſuch rare conceipt ſhould maske in ſable,</l>
               <l>which ought with glorie crownd, to be vpborne,</l>
               <l>Vnto the heauens, and plac'd at <hi>Ioues</hi> high table:</l>
               <l>Fortune, which euermore hath beene vnſtable,</l>
               <l>Enui'd thy vertues, and thy great perfection,</l>
               <l>when ſhe inchain'd thy heart, in ſuch ſubiection,</l>
               <l>Of one, that is to pay thy loue vnable,</l>
               <l>with other thing, then dumbe ſhewes of affection.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <head>A Sonet preferring the quiet life of the meane eſtate, to wealth and honors which procure enuie, and for the more part accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with danger.</head>
               <l>SVVeete is the life, that clad in baſe eſtate,</l>
               <l>Farre from the reach, of enuies hatefull ſting,</l>
               <l>Deuoid of malice, rancour, and debate,</l>
               <l>The chiefe attendants, on the court, and King,</l>
               <l>Doth yet enioy, a quiet calme content,</l>
               <l>Eſtraunged from the pompe of Princes traine,</l>
               <l>Vnto whoſe bow, there may be found no bent.</l>
               <l>Ne bounds their high aſpiring to containe:</l>
               <l>Such was the blisfull life thoſe ſheepheards led,</l>
               <l>Thoſe harmleſſe ſheepheards, that for loue ſo mourned,</l>
               <l>Piping vnto their flocke, while that they fed</l>
               <l>On the greene banks, by <hi>Flora</hi> Queene adorned;</l>
               <l>So, happie liue they, though they liue obſcurely,</l>
               <l>who liue contented, quiet, and ſecurely.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="sonnet">
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:16"/>
               <head>A Sonet in Italian, made in commendation of the Authour, and Perſwading <hi>Cynthia</hi> to leaue her ſorrow.</head>
               <l>CYnthia quel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igne che dite canoro</l>
               <l>Fe riſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onar al mondo'l chiaro nome,</l>
               <l>Laſciando in terra le terrene ſome.</l>
               <l>Salit' al ciel cant a nel' alto ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Ilor choronate di celest' all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>L'amato viſo e quell aurate chiome</l>
               <l>Che le ſue fiere voglie haueangia dome,</l>
               <l>Inuita al premie del mortal la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re.</l>
               <l>Il or ſente tuoi ſoſpir' e'l piant'e dice,</l>
               <l>Non ti lagnar non ti guastar il viſe</l>
               <l>Che toſto finir ann' it noi lamenti,</l>
               <l>Sarai tu come noi anchor felice,</l>
               <l>Alma gentil tra le beate menti</l>
               <l>Ebella piuche mai in Paradiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:10702:16"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
